<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing Tips | Alliance SciComm &amp; Consulting, LLC</title>
    <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/category/writing-tips/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://alliancescc.github.io/category/writing-tips/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Writing Tips</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Alliance SciComm &amp; Consulting © 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://alliancescc.github.io/media/icon_hue17794344b916e1e6682be2fdb405ace_12325_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Writing Tips</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/category/writing-tips/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Freewrite&#39; Method for Scientific Writing</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_freewrite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_freewrite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the importance of pre-writing &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/&#34;&gt;warm ups&lt;/a&gt;, we can’t always make it happen. Perhaps we were too preoccupied with another problem to focus during the warm up period. Or maybe a meeting ran over and we had to rush between tasks, skipping the warm up altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, if you sit down to write and your mind is blank, try the freewrite method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freewriting is a stream of consciousness method that can help direct your mind to the task at hand. Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sit down with an open word document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start typing anything that comes to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continue typing, and remind yourself what your writing task is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep typing everything that goes through your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually this mental conversation will transition entirely to the writing task at hand. It might look pretty messy, and later you’ll need to delete the extraneous text. If successful, however, you’ve added words to your draft, and that is what’s important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, it might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ugh, ok, it’s 7:30 in the morning and I’m tired but I really need to finish this writing blog. I think I’m supposed to be writing about the freewriting method, which is a method that I advocate for a lot. There’s something helpful about being able to type without worrying about what goes on the page. Anyway, so how it works is that you just sit down and start typing, and typing, and typing to see what comes out. Eventually, you can get your brain warmed up and focused on the writing task at hand.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, freewriting about the freewriting method is a bit&amp;hellip; unusual, but hopefully you’ve gotten the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve recommended the freewriting method to nearly everyone who has told me that they need to write something, but they don’t know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; to write. The beautiful part about freewriting is that it truely, does not matter what goes on the page, especially in the beginning. And even after you’ve warmed up to the topic, you can &lt;em&gt;continue&lt;/em&gt; to write in a stream of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freewriting gives you the freedom to write whatever you want about your topic, in whatever order or phrasing makes sense to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can almost guarantee that if you’ve done your literature review and are at the point to generate a first draft, the freewriting method can get &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; 70 to 80% of your content on the page. Again, yes, it will be messy writing and you’ll need to clean it up, maybe reorganize, rephrase, and refine to fit the flow of the outline. But the essential information will be there &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; you to revise, which was the initial goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To recap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freewriting is a warm-up method that can also be applied to the drafting process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/&#34;&gt;introduction and full list&lt;/a&gt; of methods for writing the first manuscript draft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Method&#39; Method for Scientific Writing</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_method/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_method/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This writing method, the method, is better described as a writing ritual. Whether or not your brain has been adequately &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/&#34;&gt;warmed up&lt;/a&gt; with a writing warm up and is ready to transition to writing, it always helps to have an external, perhaps physical, cue that it is time to write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact ritual will, of course, vary from person to person. It can also vary according to the type of writing task as the mental state and process for writing a letter of recommendation or grant is necessarily different from that of drafting a manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My preference is to make a hot cup of coffee or tea before I sit down to write. The process of making the drink, along with the soothing comfort of holding a hot mug, help me to relax and shift my focus to writing. Other rituals can be a bit more&amp;hellip; extreme, like the famous authors who &lt;a href=&#34;https://lithub.com/7-methods-for-writing-your-first-draft/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; sleep next to their manuscript, or hang upside down in anti-gravity boots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t already have a pre-writing ritual or habit, create one. Choose your ritual, whether it’s changing your sweater, eating a special snack, or putting on headphones, then make sure you repeat it &lt;em&gt;every time&lt;/em&gt; that you start to write. You may not notice much at first, but as you build the habit, you will begin responding more and more quickly to your chosen cue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lithub.com/7-methods-for-writing-your-first-draft/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; from the Literary Hub has another perspective on using the Method to write your first draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/&#34;&gt;introduction and full list&lt;/a&gt; of methods for writing the first manuscript draft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Scientific Writing Warm Ups (and Exercise) are Essential</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you tried to run, I don’t know, a mile?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was back in 2015 for me. So I know that if I tried to get up a run a mile right now, it would &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; go well. If I did finish, it would be done slowly; it doesn’t make sense for me to expect anything different. If I trained for it every day, though, then I could expect to quickly run a mile next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you wrote for more than 20 minutes in a single sitting? Or sat down to write at all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-writing-warm-ups-and-exercise-are-essential&#34;&gt;Why Writing Warm Ups (and Exercise) are Essential&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, you only do it when you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to. And since your brain is like a muscle, it doesn’t adjust well to different and larger-than-normal tasks: like writing that first 3,000 word paper or the yearly grant. Binge writing — writing only when a large task needs to be completed immediately — leaves you mentally exhausted and requires days, if not longer, to recover from. Before long, you begin to hate the idea of writing, which leads to further procrastination and a never ending cycle of binge writing and writing hangovers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another difficult (and unfair) ask for muscles are rapid transitions between tasks. An athlete doesn’t sit on the couch then compete with cold muscles; they do a warm up first, mimicking the activity they’re about to perform, which prepares their muscles for strenuous activity. Warm ups enhance muscle performance and prevent injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, it’s unfair to expect an academic to immediately transition from demanding bench work to writing on a grant. The brain needs a warm up, too. Enhanced performance in writing means time saved, and while brain injury is unlikely, do you really want to give yourself another reason to avoid writing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, academics are expecting too much of themselves when they:
(i) Binge write (i.e., run a mile without training), and
(ii) Write cold (i.e., skip a warm up activity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;whats-a-writing-warm-up&#34;&gt;What’s a Writing Warm Up?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let’s talk about what a writing warm up &lt;em&gt;is not&lt;/em&gt;. It’s not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another task that you need to fit into your day,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly complicated, or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optional for a smooth transition to writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a thought process that requires some planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, a writing warm up is using a low cognition task to create a mental buffer, or transition period, between one cognitively demanding task and another (e.g., tricky experiments and writing, or data analysis and writing). The exact low cognition task will vary from person to person and day to day, but it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; fit one criterion: it only uses muscle memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performing a low cognition task (e.g., walking, driving, washing dishes, or folding clothes) before you write allows you to begin &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt; about your writing task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending this five to ten minutes (or more) thinking about &lt;em&gt;what you are going to write before you write it&lt;/em&gt; is your writing warm up. This process cognitively transitions yourself for a productive writing session. I say it takes planning because it will take effort to identify a suitable warm up task, and remember to avoid it until immediately before your writing session. It also takes some effort to avoid mental distractions during the warm up. Writing warm ups are an essential part of my writing process now. It is satisfying to open a writing project and immediately begin typing because the words are ready and waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-do-you-practice-writing&#34;&gt;How Do You Practice Writing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, like anything else, you just do it. A lot. I’m not going to dwell here because it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; just like physical exercise; find a writing task and start with 20 minute sessions. For the days that you don’t have an essential writing task lined up, blogging, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ide.mit.edu/sites/default/files/publications/SSRN-id3039505.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;science-related Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; entries, and/or &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.reedsy.com/creative-writing-prompts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;writing prompts&lt;/a&gt; can help keep your skills honed between essential writing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bottom Line:
(i) Warm up with a low cognitive task that allows you to mentally transition to writing.
(ii) Exercise your writing “muscles” frequently with at least 3, 20 minute sessions per week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/&#34;&gt;introduction and full list&lt;/a&gt; of methods for writing the first manuscript draft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More Ideas for Writing Warmups and Exercise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Women_scientists&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Women Scientists Wikiproject&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WikiProject Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific Society Volunteer Blogs (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://asm.org/Browse-By-Content-Type/Article&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American Society for Microbiology&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ispyphysiology.com/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American Physiological Society&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://massivesci.com/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Massive Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scienceconnected.org/about-us/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science Connected&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Methods for Writing the First Manuscript Draft</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Probably one of the most frustrating parts of the scientific writing process is actually getting words to paper, aka “the first draft”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not uncommon (for me, anyway) that after finding the time and having the energy to put words to paper, they fail to present themselves. It’s a frustrating feeling that can lead to doubting myself as both a writer and an academic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I forget that the brain is like a muscle and that writing is a skill. Even the most skilled track and field athletes warm up differently to run the 100 meter dash than to throw the javelin. Furthermore, being skilled at both events requires an athlete to learn and apply two different sets of techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar concept applies to being an academic and/or scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing experiments, conducting experiments, and writing a manuscript are all essential skill sets that require distinct techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the beginning of a blog series that will explore and describe several methods and techniques (below) for approaching the drafting process. Some of these may work as “warm ups&#39;&#39; to transition your brain to the writing process. Others will be techniques to be employed directly in the drafting step. None are meant to be mutually exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this series is to provide academic writers, like yourself, with tools to personalize and improve the writing process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to experiment with them, find what works for you, and then tell me about it. What worked? What didn’t work? Why not? Perhaps your experience will make it into a future post. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drafting Techniques and Methods:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/&#34;&gt;The Warm Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_method/&#34;&gt;The Method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_freewrite/&#34;&gt;The Freewrite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Outline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Refinery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Jigsaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Spurt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Incubation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Sessional&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Set Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Tips and Tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identify the Story to Make Your Writing Process More Effective</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/central_message_narrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/central_message_narrative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deciding what to write about is generally pretty easy for a researcher. Here’s my research topic. Read. Take notes. Write the manuscript. But approaching the prewriting and drafting stages of the writing process that way can waste precious time and energy, so here are a couple of things you can do to focus your prewriting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prewriting is the first step in your journey to a manuscript or review paper. It precedes the drafting stage and is the step that will likely take the longest. During prewriting you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decide what you’re going to write about,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make an outline of your paper, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research and take notes, aka “review the literature”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it may seem straightforward (albeit overwhelming), the prewriting process is crucial to all following steps of the writing process. A haphazard approach to prewriting can result in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-essential research,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disorganized writing full of tangents, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A longer/more difficult revision process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which add up to lost time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means you need a solid prewriting strategy, which is determined in the first (seemingly shortest) action of the writing process: deciding your topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two tips to focus your ideas during step one of prewriting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;identify-the-central-message&#34;&gt;Identify the central message.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central message is one or two sentences that identify what you want your reader to know when they are done reading your scientific text. Since these are for planning purposes, they are often jargon heavy and don’t make it into your article intact. Instead, the central message helps guide you, the author, in identifying key information that needs to be included in your outline and literature review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, my dissertation work studied how the bacterium &lt;em&gt;Bacillus anthracis&lt;/em&gt; gathered iron using a small molecule called a siderophore. Siderophores are exported and used to scavenge insoluble iron from the environment. One of the siderophores that &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; uses is called petrobactin. So, when I was planning my dissertation defense the central message for my talk was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Petrobactin is &lt;a href=&#34;https://mbio.asm.org/content/9/6/e02079-18.abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;required for rapid sporulation&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; and is &lt;a href=&#34;https://mbio.asm.org/content/8/5/e01238-17.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;exported by ApeX&lt;/a&gt;, but petrobactin fragments can support &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is jargon heavy and did not become an explicit sentence in my defense. However, it narrows down the information that will be included. For instance, if I’m discussing petrobactin use by &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt;, then I don’t need to discuss other bacteria that may use petrobactin (which is important information for a review paper about petrobactin). Additionally, if I’m focusing on the role of petrobactin in sporulation, then I can keep my discussion of spore germination to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;identify-your-scientific-narrative&#34;&gt;Identify your scientific narrative.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative is going to be the overarching structure of your paper. Like the central message, this is jargon heavy and will not be directly included in the body of your paper. However, it helps further guide you in determining the information that needs to be included and what information or concepts are tangential. The most generalized narrative structure was characterized by Randy Olson in his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/H/bo21174162.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Houston, We Have a Narrative&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Here, Olson describes the ABT narrative structure, which is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And,&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;But,&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Therefore.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it appears unassuming, the ABT narrative has a lot to offer scientists. There’s too much to cover in this blog post, so here’s an overview (an ABT workshop will be offered in the future). Most stories can be crafted with a single ABT wherein the AND lays the background information and context, the BUT introduces a conflict or something unexpected, and the THEREFORE describes a solution or conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, this article was drafted from a brief ABT narrative:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A - What is prewriting AND what steps are generally included in the first stage,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B - BUT a poor prewriting strategy can cause problems,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T - THEREFORE, here are two key concepts (central message and ABT) to guide the author through the writing process more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look back at the overall structure of this blog post, you can see how my ABT forms the skeleton of the writing. Similarly, the ABT helps inform my overall outline, as well as what information is relevant or not. In the ABT, I’ve committed myself to tips that make prewriting more effective for an organized draft. That means I’m not discussing how to manage references. While that’s important and easily locating your references makes adding citations more efficient, it doesn’t directly contribute to the organization of your writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, each science story, or manuscript, requires two distinct narrative ABTs. The first is the Question ABT, which generally provides the skeleton of the introduction, rationale, and methodology of the study. The second is the Answer ABT, which describes and organizes the results and their discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the example of my dissertation defense, the narrative describing my first research paper on export of petrobactin from &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known siderophore-associated proteins are upregulated in low iron conditions AND some known siderophore exporters belong to these different transport protein families. BUT there are many potential siderophore exporters in &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt;. THEREFORE, we have developed a bioinformatics protocol to target potential petrobactin exporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After screening many different potential exporters, petrobactin is exported from the ApeX protein AND accumulates in the cell pellet of ΔApeX mutants. BUT ΔApeX exports functional petrobactin fragments THEREFORE it can still cause disease in mice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ABTs helped identify the structure of the outline and was particularly helpful in deciding the order in which data should be introduced in the results section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By identifying the central message and narrative of your scientific text, you can help eliminate tangential information. Additionally, having a handle on the eventual narrative of your research paper can prevent a dense, unorganized data-dump draft.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Tips to Organize Thesis and Article Sources</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/organize_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/organize_research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the course of a literature review, you may come across hundreds of research papers that will contribute to your understanding of the field and possibly even be cited in a manuscript. So how do you keep track of these sources?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write an annotated bibliography&lt;/strong&gt; - An annotated bibliography is going to be a list of the sources that you’ve read along with important notes to explain the source’s importance and relevance to your research. While some people do this by hand, that can be laborious, particularly when you are searching for a source after the fact. My suggestion for the modern annotated bibliography is to use a searchable format such as Word, Rmarkdown, OneNote, or EndNote, etc. That will allow you to easily re-reference a source and (re)identify sources that talk about particular concepts. Below is a list of components to include in each entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citation&lt;/strong&gt; - In addition to the author(s) and year of publication, you should also make a note of the doi (so you can find it later using &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/[insert doi]&lt;/a&gt;), and the filename of the pdf. The filename is especially important since it allows you to find the pdf you already have, without opening 20 files one-by-one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt; - Are any of the methods used especially relevant to your work? This might be because you need the protocol, they are key to interpreting the data, and/or are insufficient (i.e., they provide an opportunity for you to improve the field).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt; - What are the key results and findings? What figure is central to their story?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Limitations&lt;/strong&gt; - What are the limitations of the research? What could be done differently to improve the robustness of the research?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; - What do you think about the paper? Use this as an opportunity to present your unfiltered thoughts, feelings, musings, and big ideas. That way you can find them later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow up&lt;/strong&gt; - Are there any references that you should read in the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep a spreadsheet&lt;/strong&gt; - Spreadsheets are another option for keeping track of the sources you have identified in a searchable and easy to skim format. In this case, you would likely have more information about the source’s origins, citations, accessibility, etc. (See &amp;ldquo;Organizing Sources&amp;rdquo; in the resources below for a template)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use a citation management system&lt;/strong&gt; - Some citation management systems are great for keeping track of relevant sources. Mendeley is a particularly good option because you can import, read, highlight, annotate, and search for a pdf. However, it has undergone some recent changes that make it more difficult to use and transfer your references if necessary. (See the resources below for some handy web tools)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://habitsofatravellingarchaeologist.com/tips-for-organizing-sources-for-research-papers/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tips for Organizing Sources for Research Papers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://research.ewu.edu/c.php?g=53632&amp;amp;p=2986487&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Organizing Sources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://beryliveylibrary.wordpress.com/2018/02/13/organize-research/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;What’s the best way to organize my research?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lifewire.com/organize-research-3483046&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Organize Your Research With These Free Web Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where to Start (and When to Stop) a Lit Review</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/when_to_stop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/when_to_stop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When it comes to a literature review for thesis and article writing, everyone has the same three questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where do I start?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When do I stop?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I stay organized?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we’ll cover some tips for answering the first two questions. Next week’s post will address organizing sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-do-i-start-the-lit-review&#34;&gt;Where do I start the lit review?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The big picture&lt;/strong&gt; - It’s important to first get a sense of the overall field, and where you’ll begin with this depends on your level of experience in the field. If you are completely new to the field, then beginning with a relevant Wikipedia article may be right for you. Like academic literature, &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/357/6351/557.2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wikipedia entries&lt;/a&gt; have references which can point you to relevant articles in the literature. However, if you’re familiar with the field and haven’t done an in depth literature review in it  yet, then reading both a dated (at least 5 to 10 years old) and a recent (in the last 1 to 2 years) review article can help you understand the overall progress of the field and identify important articles and themes. Finally, those with high experience and knowledge in the field may choose to begin by reviewing the most recent publications using Google Scholar or a similar source.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-where-to-begin-a-literature-review-according-to-your-experience-in-the-field&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Where to begin a literature review, according to your experience in the field.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/when_to_stop/getting_started_hu814c3514c9a5683f64f0cfd0704540bd_153939_39114ecd443bc34fefdfbd9c84e6a2d3.png 400w,
               /post/when_to_stop/getting_started_hu814c3514c9a5683f64f0cfd0704540bd_153939_392e119aa0126a61fd7c569dc183ad23.png 760w,
               /post/when_to_stop/getting_started_hu814c3514c9a5683f64f0cfd0704540bd_153939_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/when_to_stop/getting_started_hu814c3514c9a5683f64f0cfd0704540bd_153939_39114ecd443bc34fefdfbd9c84e6a2d3.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;313&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Where to begin a literature review, according to your experience in the field.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The outline&lt;/strong&gt; - Before you begin the literature review, you should have developed an &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/why_outline/&#34;&gt;outline&lt;/a&gt;. Now that you have an understanding of the big picture, re-evaluate the outline for missing pieces, logical flow, and potential redundancies. If things seem overwhelming, pick a topic or subtopic to begin your research at. You could either ease into the process by choosing a topic you know fairly well, or pick the area where you are the weakest and know you will need to spend the most time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-do-i-stop-reading-and-start-writing&#34;&gt;When do I stop reading and start writing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set a deadline&lt;/strong&gt; - Consider allocating a specific amount of time to the initial research stage of your writing process. This may help you be more efficient with your research time and gives a non-negotiable deadline to start putting words to paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep track&lt;/strong&gt; - Keep a log or journal where you note the search terms and databases that you have used to find sources. Have you exhausted your options? If so, consider asking a colleague or your advisor if they have additional suggestions for search terms and/or resources. If not, or you feel confident with your search thus far, then it might be time to start your first draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update your outline&lt;/strong&gt; - The outline should help guide your reading and information gathering, and should be updated as you work through each topic and subtopic. When each section seems to have a reasonable number of points, then you probably have enough information for the first draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check your mental load&lt;/strong&gt; - Sometimes you will come across a new piece of information or perspective that will shift your thought process. Sometimes there will be so much information in your head that there doesn’t seem to be room for any more. Any time there are thoughts that seem to be swirling, then it’s time to put them to paper. Maybe this means that after spending a few days on a subtopic your brain feels overwhelmed, so you stop and draft a few paragraphs before you move on to the next. Or maybe you’ll research 50% or 90%, or even 100%, of the outline before this happens and you stop for a few days to get all of the information out of your head and onto paper. Either way, figuring out what works for you will give you a better idea of when it’s time to stop reading and start writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t stress&lt;/strong&gt; - Remember that &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/writing_process/&#34;&gt;writing is iterative&lt;/a&gt; so you can always (and probably will) come back to the research stage later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://libguides.uwf.edu/c.php?g=215199&amp;amp;p=1420520&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LibGuides: Literature Review: Conducting &amp;amp; Writing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scribbr.com/dissertation/literature-review/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Literature Review | A Complete Step-by-Step Guide&lt;/a&gt; - Good tips for review papers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why an Outline is Necessary for Science Writing</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/why_outline/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/why_outline/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The next step in the prewriting process is the outline, but what is it and why should you make one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, you should have your topic, &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/central_message_narrative/&#34;&gt;central message, and narrative&lt;/a&gt;. You will build on those to create an outline, the next layer in organizing your paper before you begin to write. But aside from personal preference, why create an outline at all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To save yourself time and effort. The outline serves several purposes that all contribute to reducing the amount of revision your first draft will need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Reduce mental load.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, there are probably a lot of bits and pieces of your paper that are floating around in your head. The outline is a perfect place to keep these for future use. Getting them out and onto paper frees up a lot of brainspace, which you’ll need for the research stage of prewriting. Additionally, the bullet point format will demonstrate the areas where you either have, or lack, expertise. And now you have a handy structure to add information &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; during your literature review to help track your progress .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Improve organization.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bullet point format is also helpful for preempting repetitive information and making connections between topics to improve the overall flow of your manuscript. By outlining each section and their paragraphs first, you can ensure that each paragraph is essential in advancing your narrative and more easily identify (and rearrange) related information or logical connections to aid topic transitions. If you’re feeling stuck, there are outline prompts and resources at the bottom of the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Ensure advisor compatibility.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can feel pretty defeating to write a 4,000 word first draft that your advisor either completely rearranges or scraps. Avoid that frustration for both you and your advisor by presenting them with a detailed outline. Going over the outline with your advisor can help eliminate potential problems by identifying areas that will need to be expanded, moved, or eliminated all together. Working with your advisor on the outline will also give both of you confidence in the drafting process, since you both have an understanding of what will be discussed and the order. To get the most out of the discussion, consider waiting until you have a more detailed post-literature review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/writing_process/&#34;&gt;the writing process is messy&lt;/a&gt;, so your first outline won’t be perfect. Instead, much like your final product, it will be in constant flux until you’ve moved past the revision stage. The upside is that it’s easier to change bulleted text instead of prose!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outline-prompts&#34;&gt;Outline Prompts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction or Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What information and/or context will the reader need to adequately understand everything that will be presented in the results?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the rationale for the study? What gap is it addressing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What key techniques were used in the study?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results (each subsection)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the rationale for the experiment, what question will it answer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the key points of setup that the reader needs to know to draw conclusions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the possible conclusions from this experiment? What would the results be for each outcome?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What were the results?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is your conclusion based on the described results?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion or Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly, what were the major results and conclusions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put your findings in context with other studies, where do they line up or contradict?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do these findings mean for the field at large?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the limitations to your conclusions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you want your reader to do and/or remember from your results?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uncw.edu/ulc/documents/organizationofanacademicpaper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Organization of a Traditional Academic Paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://writingcenter.fas.harvard.edu/pages/outlining&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Outlining&lt;/a&gt; - Good tips for organizing a review paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://owl.purdue.edu/owl/general_writing/the_writing_process/developing_an_outline/how_to_outline.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How to Outline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Writing is Messy. That’s Perfect.</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/writing_process/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/writing_process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The scientific writing process can be summarized in five steps: prewriting, drafting, revising, editing, and finally… publication. It seems straightforward, but also&amp;hellip; overwhelming. Especially when you’re tasked with starting at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that while writing is a lot of work, it can be made more approachable. This post is the first in a series that will explore the writing process and break it down into actionable pieces, with an emphasis on writing in the biological and biosciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll begin by describing the overall writing process and workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prewriting - generate ideas, identify evidence and sources, and craft outlines&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drafting - transform the outline into logically connected sentences and paragraphs, add evidence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revising - reorganize the draft, add evidence, eliminate tangents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editing - correct misspellings and grammar, check citations and figures&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publication - submit for grading (or peer review)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, the general process appears to be linear.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-what-we-think-the-writing-process-is-like-linear&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;What we think the writing process is like. Linear.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/writing_process/writing_process_linear_hu505d8ad4a4021a1134ad263daf931d17_5271_0049405cc553350ed823b5900c083896.png 400w,
               /post/writing_process/writing_process_linear_hu505d8ad4a4021a1134ad263daf931d17_5271_d68ab58266e02ccefd1577c5d368cbd7.png 760w,
               /post/writing_process/writing_process_linear_hu505d8ad4a4021a1134ad263daf931d17_5271_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/writing_process/writing_process_linear_hu505d8ad4a4021a1134ad263daf931d17_5271_0049405cc553350ed823b5900c083896.png&#34;
               width=&#34;344&#34;
               height=&#34;726&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      What we think the writing process is like. Linear.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in practice, the effective writing process is quite a bit messier (image 2). For instance, after writing a first draft, the author often identifies topics that need more elaboration and/or evidence, which send them back through the prewriting and drafting steps. Even after a manuscript is done and submitted to a research advisor or reviewer, it often comes back with requests for revision. To accomplish those revisions, the author may need to revisit the prewriting and drafting steps again, followed by revising and editing for resubmission.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-better-representation-of-the-writing-process-iterative&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A better representation of the writing process. Iterative.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/writing_process/writing_process_messy_hu737c7f8e29dd2bae9f0b8b1a5bf0de99_9007_ba050413a17c9aac9341df1b6d94bdca.png 400w,
               /post/writing_process/writing_process_messy_hu737c7f8e29dd2bae9f0b8b1a5bf0de99_9007_5e26e89e0405d74ff2613b8fc5e50362.png 760w,
               /post/writing_process/writing_process_messy_hu737c7f8e29dd2bae9f0b8b1a5bf0de99_9007_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/writing_process/writing_process_messy_hu737c7f8e29dd2bae9f0b8b1a5bf0de99_9007_ba050413a17c9aac9341df1b6d94bdca.png&#34;
               width=&#34;586&#34;
               height=&#34;609&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A better representation of the writing process. Iterative.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, the real writing process may seem even more overwhelming. After all, how are you supposed to know when to move forward or backward? How will you know when you’re done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are valid fears, and the beauty of an iterative writing process is that you don’t really have to answer them. Approaching writing as an iterative process, as opposed to linear, has multiple advantages. Some of these include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reduced pressure for first drafts,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More realistic writing expectations,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More accurate writing timeline, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having sections in different stages of the process allows for workload flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific writing is an act of creativity that requires freedom to think, synthesize, and explore new ideas. Removing the pressure for the first draft to be perfect, or near perfect, allows you as a writer to start the writing process more creatively with bigger, messier ideas. As the ideas are refined, they might lead to unexpected connections and conclusions, but it’s hard to know unless they are given voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, because you begin the process knowing that prewriting, drafting, and revising will be revisited, there is less pressure for each step to be “complete” before moving on to the next. Set goals for the amount of time of words that you’ll spend on each step and when you’re done, start over. The more you write, the more accurate expectations you can develop for the time and effort spent at each step, leading to more accurate writing timelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An added bonus is that you can break down the writing task into smaller chunks, and work through the writing process for each individual section. If you have sections at varying stages (e.g., introduction is in prewriting, methods are in revising, discussion is in drafting), then you have freedom in the type of writing you will accomplish on any given day. Tired of putting words on the page? Read literature and work on prewriting the introduction. Mentally burnt out but still want to make progress? Add citations to the methods section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ Writing is not a linear process, like following a recipe to bake a cake.” Teaching Elementary School Students to Be Effective Writers, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ies.ed.gov/ncee/wwc/Docs/PracticeGuide/writing_pg_062612.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pg 14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the demands of a linear writing process seem overwhelming to you. It’s understandable. Approaching writing as an iterative process may help overcome some of the mental obstacles in the way of your next writing task. This brief overview of the writing process will be followed by posts exploring each step in more detail and providing strategies to tackle them. For now, if your best laid writing plans aren’t working out, don’t feel alone. Writing is messy. And that’s perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liferichpublishing.com/AuthorResources/General/5-Step-Writing-Process.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The 5-Step Writing Process: From Brainstorming to Publishing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bowenpeters.weebly.com/uploads/8/1/1/9/8119969/writing_process_detailed.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Writing Process 5 Basic Stages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ies.ed.gov/ncee/wwc/Docs/PracticeGuide/writing_pg_062612.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Teaching Elementary School Students to Be Effective Writers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for Getting Writing Done in Pandemic Purgatory</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/pandemic_purgatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/pandemic_purgatory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of January, one month before Michigan responded to the pandemic by closing non-essential services, I pulled my 3-year-old from daycare. I was (and still am) attempting to launch a business, but our back up funds had run dry and we could no longer afford childcare. As it happened, I got an early taste of the pandemic dilemma that millions have faced since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work is a large part of my identity and in this extended lack of childcare, my brain will not turn off. Unlike many, I don’t have the external motivating factors of an institution who demands more than I can give, but neither can I put my work on hold to embrace the single job of stay-at-home parenting. The internal motivators, and the normalcy that it provides, are too strong. So, like many others I am stuck in this pandemic purgatory where housework, childcare, and my own motivations are in constant opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some things I’ve learned while trying to live, and write, in my purgatory. Perhaps they will be helpful for others. The caveat is that while I solo parent during the work day (6am to ??),  I do have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/parents/learning/view/covid-19-pandemic-privilege?__vfz=medium%3Dsharebar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;many pandemic privileges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that may affect how well these tips work for you. That said, here are my suggestions for maintaining sanity-saving levels of writing and productivity in our collective pandemic purgatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;keep-up-with-self-care&#34;&gt;Keep up with self-care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing is a creative act that consumes a lot of mental energy, so self-care remains as important as ever.  In addition to the existential threat of a pandemic, the availability of digital workplaces (e.g., Zoom, Slack, Google Drive) enables (even enforces) bringing our work lives home in an unprecedented way, creating unprecedented stress. Whether it’s paying the bills, making the (virtual) therapy appointment, or taking a bath, we must provide ourselves with the opportunity to reduce our stress levels whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already know that humans need adequate sleep to be productive. In fact, the stress created by sleep deprivation can reduce the productivity of any time gained. Similarly, the excessive amount of work-from-home-and-homeschool-my-child-during-a-pandemic stress might cause post-lunch exhaustion or irritability. That’s your cue to take a nap, work out, or practice a similar stress-relief technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-delegating&#34;&gt;Practice delegating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can accept taking my car to a mechanic for an oil change, but when it comes to my work, I’m the queen of “Oh, I’ll just do it myself.” That approach used to work, since I had childcare and the luxury of time and focus to figure it out. Now that I don’t have either, I’ve finally realized that I need to delegate tasks that don’t absolutely require my skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you really have the mental load available to learn Adobe Illustrator right now? Probably not, so find a professional to make your graphic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you read your grant proposal so many times that you have it memorized? Now’s the time to have a professional editor look it over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you facepalming to the tune of R errors? Find a data analyst and get some help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delegation (i.e., trusting someone else with &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; work) is tough, but essential to retain your limited mental load, sanity, and productivity. Additionally, plenty of small businesses and freelancers could use the extra business right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bargain&#34;&gt;Bargain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My son loves the new norm of virtually unlimited access to me. I had difficulty adjusting. It would be difficult to negotiate the abrupt transition from the traditional 9 to 5 to our new work conditions alone, but adding children, roommates, and/or partners makes it all the more difficult. That’s why I suggest just that, negotiating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the upheaval of our lives and validating the fears, frustrations, and desires of our fellow captives is the first step to establishing a functional household. My son’s desire for a constant playmate and parent is valid and expected, but counterproductive to my own mental health. So, I negotiate boundaries that enable both of us to get what we need. These are some of the resources that have resulted in productive negotiations in our household.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;time&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not very good at schedules, but I have an ideal schedule&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that alternates between work and play. I make it very clear that I have to work for 2 hours, after which we will do whatever activity he chooses. Then I set a timer and stick to our agreement. After lunch, another 2 hours are blocked out for “quiet time”, i.e., I work and he naps or plays in his room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another strategy to negotiate time is pushing back bedtime. My son doesn’t nap and tends to function in 12 hour sleep/wake cycles; unless my depression is acting up, I get up with my husband at 6 am. With a standard 8/9pm bedtime, this allows me one to two hours of uninterrupted work. Mornings are my most productive time of the day, so to maximize my time we started allowing my son to stay up later, and later, and later. Eventually, he was going to bed around midnight (hubby is a night owl) and sleeping until almost 11am. Hello half a work day! Disclaimer: This only worked a few weeks. Then he fell asleep at 5pm one night, woke up at 6am and we were back where we started &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;desirables&#34;&gt;Desirables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After work versus play time has been negotiated, we enter the “desirable” bargain (aka bribing) phase. Here, my son requests something that will better facilitate his solo play time. A common request is screen time, which is an automatic given for the “quiet time” described above. If his tablet isn’t available, I generally give up my phone for him to watch videos. YouTube for Kids is pretty dicy, so instead I open either Netflix or the &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt; PBS Video app, which features favorites like Daniel Tiger and the Kratt brothers. Sometimes, a favorite snack or treat is the missing ingredient to successful solo play. My son most often requests hot chocolate or an ice pop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, there aren’t any desirables that will facilitate work/writing time. Instead, he wants to do an activity “with you!” and we negotiate attention for proximity. I pick a task that I can do with slightly less focused mental labor, and sit next to him while he plays or watches a favorite show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;find-accountability&#34;&gt;Find accountability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if we have found the time and mental space to work, it’s easy to get distracted by the latest Twitter dumpster fire. This is where accountability comes into play. Find an accountability partner to set goals with and report back to. Having defined goals helps prevent the “what am I doing” overwhelm that often leads (me) to Twitter. Alternately, you and your accountability partner(s) could schedule video calls during overlapping work hours. Not for talking, but for working in tandem, which facilitates focus for both of you. An added bonus is having adult human contact to look forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific productivity is a core component of my identity and a symbol of normalcy that maintains my sanity. Taking care of myself, working with my fellow housemates, delegating tasks, and finding accountability have all been integral to maintaining any level of productivity.  While the above suggestions may not &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; like writing tips, they all contribute to that first essential step of writing: doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pandemic Privileges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My husband has continued working, so we have not lost our primary income&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a large house with a yard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have technology: TV, internet, computers, tablet, phones, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have the cash flow and space to store food to minimize exposure and reduce stress&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have our own transportation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly, my ideal schedule is to work from 6:30 am until my son wakes up. Then we take a breakfast break and he plays/has screen time for another couple of hours. At 11am we go outside until lunch at 12:30. After lunch is a 2 hour &amp;ldquo;quiet time&amp;rdquo; followed by chores and my workout. Then it&amp;rsquo;s snack time, after which we play whatever my son wants until it&amp;rsquo;s time for dinner, bath, and bed.














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-suggested-workplay-schedule&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A suggested work/play schedule&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/pandemic_purgatory/schedule_hu1f2cd1589726743794d8c2ad2031bae0_47995_14069fe221cc468da1ae31ac6054985c.png 400w,
               /post/pandemic_purgatory/schedule_hu1f2cd1589726743794d8c2ad2031bae0_47995_bec3c2e0778ce5d1a9d6e6a87b8a1aee.png 760w,
               /post/pandemic_purgatory/schedule_hu1f2cd1589726743794d8c2ad2031bae0_47995_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/pandemic_purgatory/schedule_hu1f2cd1589726743794d8c2ad2031bae0_47995_14069fe221cc468da1ae31ac6054985c.png&#34;
               width=&#34;688&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A suggested work/play schedule
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
