<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing | Alliance SciComm &amp; Consulting, LLC</title>
    <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/tag/writing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://alliancescc.github.io/tag/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Writing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Alliance SciComm &amp; Consulting © 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://alliancescc.github.io/media/icon_hue17794344b916e1e6682be2fdb405ace_12325_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/tag/writing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Freewrite&#39; Method for Scientific Writing</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_freewrite/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_freewrite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the importance of pre-writing &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/&#34;&gt;warm ups&lt;/a&gt;, we can’t always make it happen. Perhaps we were too preoccupied with another problem to focus during the warm up period. Or maybe a meeting ran over and we had to rush between tasks, skipping the warm up altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, if you sit down to write and your mind is blank, try the freewrite method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freewriting is a stream of consciousness method that can help direct your mind to the task at hand. Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sit down with an open word document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start typing anything that comes to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continue typing, and remind yourself what your writing task is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep typing everything that goes through your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually this mental conversation will transition entirely to the writing task at hand. It might look pretty messy, and later you’ll need to delete the extraneous text. If successful, however, you’ve added words to your draft, and that is what’s important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, it might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ugh, ok, it’s 7:30 in the morning and I’m tired but I really need to finish this writing blog. I think I’m supposed to be writing about the freewriting method, which is a method that I advocate for a lot. There’s something helpful about being able to type without worrying about what goes on the page. Anyway, so how it works is that you just sit down and start typing, and typing, and typing to see what comes out. Eventually, you can get your brain warmed up and focused on the writing task at hand.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, freewriting about the freewriting method is a bit&amp;hellip; unusual, but hopefully you’ve gotten the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve recommended the freewriting method to nearly everyone who has told me that they need to write something, but they don’t know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; to write. The beautiful part about freewriting is that it truely, does not matter what goes on the page, especially in the beginning. And even after you’ve warmed up to the topic, you can &lt;em&gt;continue&lt;/em&gt; to write in a stream of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freewriting gives you the freedom to write whatever you want about your topic, in whatever order or phrasing makes sense to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can almost guarantee that if you’ve done your literature review and are at the point to generate a first draft, the freewriting method can get &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; 70 to 80% of your content on the page. Again, yes, it will be messy writing and you’ll need to clean it up, maybe reorganize, rephrase, and refine to fit the flow of the outline. But the essential information will be there &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; you to revise, which was the initial goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To recap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freewriting is a warm-up method that can also be applied to the drafting process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/&#34;&gt;introduction and full list&lt;/a&gt; of methods for writing the first manuscript draft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Method&#39; Method for Scientific Writing</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_method/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_method/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This writing method, the method, is better described as a writing ritual. Whether or not your brain has been adequately &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/&#34;&gt;warmed up&lt;/a&gt; with a writing warm up and is ready to transition to writing, it always helps to have an external, perhaps physical, cue that it is time to write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact ritual will, of course, vary from person to person. It can also vary according to the type of writing task as the mental state and process for writing a letter of recommendation or grant is necessarily different from that of drafting a manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My preference is to make a hot cup of coffee or tea before I sit down to write. The process of making the drink, along with the soothing comfort of holding a hot mug, help me to relax and shift my focus to writing. Other rituals can be a bit more&amp;hellip; extreme, like the famous authors who &lt;a href=&#34;https://lithub.com/7-methods-for-writing-your-first-draft/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; sleep next to their manuscript, or hang upside down in anti-gravity boots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t already have a pre-writing ritual or habit, create one. Choose your ritual, whether it’s changing your sweater, eating a special snack, or putting on headphones, then make sure you repeat it &lt;em&gt;every time&lt;/em&gt; that you start to write. You may not notice much at first, but as you build the habit, you will begin responding more and more quickly to your chosen cue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lithub.com/7-methods-for-writing-your-first-draft/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; from the Literary Hub has another perspective on using the Method to write your first draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/&#34;&gt;introduction and full list&lt;/a&gt; of methods for writing the first manuscript draft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Scientific Writing Warm Ups (and Exercise) are Essential</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you tried to run, I don’t know, a mile?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was back in 2015 for me. So I know that if I tried to get up a run a mile right now, it would &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; go well. If I did finish, it would be done slowly; it doesn’t make sense for me to expect anything different. If I trained for it every day, though, then I could expect to quickly run a mile next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you wrote for more than 20 minutes in a single sitting? Or sat down to write at all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-writing-warm-ups-and-exercise-are-essential&#34;&gt;Why Writing Warm Ups (and Exercise) are Essential&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, you only do it when you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to. And since your brain is like a muscle, it doesn’t adjust well to different and larger-than-normal tasks: like writing that first 3,000 word paper or the yearly grant. Binge writing — writing only when a large task needs to be completed immediately — leaves you mentally exhausted and requires days, if not longer, to recover from. Before long, you begin to hate the idea of writing, which leads to further procrastination and a never ending cycle of binge writing and writing hangovers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another difficult (and unfair) ask for muscles are rapid transitions between tasks. An athlete doesn’t sit on the couch then compete with cold muscles; they do a warm up first, mimicking the activity they’re about to perform, which prepares their muscles for strenuous activity. Warm ups enhance muscle performance and prevent injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, it’s unfair to expect an academic to immediately transition from demanding bench work to writing on a grant. The brain needs a warm up, too. Enhanced performance in writing means time saved, and while brain injury is unlikely, do you really want to give yourself another reason to avoid writing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, academics are expecting too much of themselves when they:
(i) Binge write (i.e., run a mile without training), and
(ii) Write cold (i.e., skip a warm up activity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;whats-a-writing-warm-up&#34;&gt;What’s a Writing Warm Up?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let’s talk about what a writing warm up &lt;em&gt;is not&lt;/em&gt;. It’s not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another task that you need to fit into your day,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly complicated, or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optional for a smooth transition to writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a thought process that requires some planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, a writing warm up is using a low cognition task to create a mental buffer, or transition period, between one cognitively demanding task and another (e.g., tricky experiments and writing, or data analysis and writing). The exact low cognition task will vary from person to person and day to day, but it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; fit one criterion: it only uses muscle memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performing a low cognition task (e.g., walking, driving, washing dishes, or folding clothes) before you write allows you to begin &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt; about your writing task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending this five to ten minutes (or more) thinking about &lt;em&gt;what you are going to write before you write it&lt;/em&gt; is your writing warm up. This process cognitively transitions yourself for a productive writing session. I say it takes planning because it will take effort to identify a suitable warm up task, and remember to avoid it until immediately before your writing session. It also takes some effort to avoid mental distractions during the warm up. Writing warm ups are an essential part of my writing process now. It is satisfying to open a writing project and immediately begin typing because the words are ready and waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-do-you-practice-writing&#34;&gt;How Do You Practice Writing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, like anything else, you just do it. A lot. I’m not going to dwell here because it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; just like physical exercise; find a writing task and start with 20 minute sessions. For the days that you don’t have an essential writing task lined up, blogging, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ide.mit.edu/sites/default/files/publications/SSRN-id3039505.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;science-related Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; entries, and/or &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.reedsy.com/creative-writing-prompts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;writing prompts&lt;/a&gt; can help keep your skills honed between essential writing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bottom Line:
(i) Warm up with a low cognitive task that allows you to mentally transition to writing.
(ii) Exercise your writing “muscles” frequently with at least 3, 20 minute sessions per week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/&#34;&gt;introduction and full list&lt;/a&gt; of methods for writing the first manuscript draft.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More Ideas for Writing Warmups and Exercise&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Women_scientists&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Women Scientists Wikiproject&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WikiProject Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific Society Volunteer Blogs (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://asm.org/Browse-By-Content-Type/Article&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American Society for Microbiology&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ispyphysiology.com/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American Physiological Society&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://massivesci.com/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Massive Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scienceconnected.org/about-us/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science Connected&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Methods for Writing the First Manuscript Draft</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Probably one of the most frustrating parts of the scientific writing process is actually getting words to paper, aka “the first draft”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not uncommon (for me, anyway) that after finding the time and having the energy to put words to paper, they fail to present themselves. It’s a frustrating feeling that can lead to doubting myself as both a writer and an academic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I forget that the brain is like a muscle and that writing is a skill. Even the most skilled track and field athletes warm up differently to run the 100 meter dash than to throw the javelin. Furthermore, being skilled at both events requires an athlete to learn and apply two different sets of techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar concept applies to being an academic and/or scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing experiments, conducting experiments, and writing a manuscript are all essential skill sets that require distinct techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the beginning of a blog series that will explore and describe several methods and techniques (below) for approaching the drafting process. Some of these may work as “warm ups&#39;&#39; to transition your brain to the writing process. Others will be techniques to be employed directly in the drafting step. None are meant to be mutually exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this series is to provide academic writers, like yourself, with tools to personalize and improve the writing process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to experiment with them, find what works for you, and then tell me about it. What worked? What didn’t work? Why not? Perhaps your experience will make it into a future post. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drafting Techniques and Methods:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_warm_up/&#34;&gt;The Warm Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_method/&#34;&gt;The Method&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alliancescc.github.io/post/draft_methods_freewrite/&#34;&gt;The Freewrite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Outline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Refinery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Jigsaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Spurt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Incubation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Sessional&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;The Set Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Tips and Tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identify the Story to Make Your Writing Process More Effective</title>
      <link>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/central_message_narrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alliancescc.github.io/post/central_message_narrative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deciding what to write about is generally pretty easy for a researcher. Here’s my research topic. Read. Take notes. Write the manuscript. But approaching the prewriting and drafting stages of the writing process that way can waste precious time and energy, so here are a couple of things you can do to focus your prewriting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prewriting is the first step in your journey to a manuscript or review paper. It precedes the drafting stage and is the step that will likely take the longest. During prewriting you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decide what you’re going to write about,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make an outline of your paper, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research and take notes, aka “review the literature”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it may seem straightforward (albeit overwhelming), the prewriting process is crucial to all following steps of the writing process. A haphazard approach to prewriting can result in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-essential research,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disorganized writing full of tangents, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A longer/more difficult revision process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which add up to lost time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means you need a solid prewriting strategy, which is determined in the first (seemingly shortest) action of the writing process: deciding your topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two tips to focus your ideas during step one of prewriting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;identify-the-central-message&#34;&gt;Identify the central message.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central message is one or two sentences that identify what you want your reader to know when they are done reading your scientific text. Since these are for planning purposes, they are often jargon heavy and don’t make it into your article intact. Instead, the central message helps guide you, the author, in identifying key information that needs to be included in your outline and literature review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, my dissertation work studied how the bacterium &lt;em&gt;Bacillus anthracis&lt;/em&gt; gathered iron using a small molecule called a siderophore. Siderophores are exported and used to scavenge insoluble iron from the environment. One of the siderophores that &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; uses is called petrobactin. So, when I was planning my dissertation defense the central message for my talk was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Petrobactin is &lt;a href=&#34;https://mbio.asm.org/content/9/6/e02079-18.abstract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;required for rapid sporulation&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; and is &lt;a href=&#34;https://mbio.asm.org/content/8/5/e01238-17.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;exported by ApeX&lt;/a&gt;, but petrobactin fragments can support &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; disease.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is jargon heavy and did not become an explicit sentence in my defense. However, it narrows down the information that will be included. For instance, if I’m discussing petrobactin use by &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt;, then I don’t need to discuss other bacteria that may use petrobactin (which is important information for a review paper about petrobactin). Additionally, if I’m focusing on the role of petrobactin in sporulation, then I can keep my discussion of spore germination to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;identify-your-scientific-narrative&#34;&gt;Identify your scientific narrative.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative is going to be the overarching structure of your paper. Like the central message, this is jargon heavy and will not be directly included in the body of your paper. However, it helps further guide you in determining the information that needs to be included and what information or concepts are tangential. The most generalized narrative structure was characterized by Randy Olson in his book &lt;a href=&#34;https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/H/bo21174162.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Houston, We Have a Narrative&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Here, Olson describes the ABT narrative structure, which is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And,&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;But,&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Therefore.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it appears unassuming, the ABT narrative has a lot to offer scientists. There’s too much to cover in this blog post, so here’s an overview (an ABT workshop will be offered in the future). Most stories can be crafted with a single ABT wherein the AND lays the background information and context, the BUT introduces a conflict or something unexpected, and the THEREFORE describes a solution or conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, this article was drafted from a brief ABT narrative:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A - What is prewriting AND what steps are generally included in the first stage,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B - BUT a poor prewriting strategy can cause problems,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T - THEREFORE, here are two key concepts (central message and ABT) to guide the author through the writing process more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look back at the overall structure of this blog post, you can see how my ABT forms the skeleton of the writing. Similarly, the ABT helps inform my overall outline, as well as what information is relevant or not. In the ABT, I’ve committed myself to tips that make prewriting more effective for an organized draft. That means I’m not discussing how to manage references. While that’s important and easily locating your references makes adding citations more efficient, it doesn’t directly contribute to the organization of your writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, each science story, or manuscript, requires two distinct narrative ABTs. The first is the Question ABT, which generally provides the skeleton of the introduction, rationale, and methodology of the study. The second is the Answer ABT, which describes and organizes the results and their discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to the example of my dissertation defense, the narrative describing my first research paper on export of petrobactin from &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt; was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Known siderophore-associated proteins are upregulated in low iron conditions AND some known siderophore exporters belong to these different transport protein families. BUT there are many potential siderophore exporters in &lt;em&gt;B. anthracis&lt;/em&gt;. THEREFORE, we have developed a bioinformatics protocol to target potential petrobactin exporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After screening many different potential exporters, petrobactin is exported from the ApeX protein AND accumulates in the cell pellet of ΔApeX mutants. BUT ΔApeX exports functional petrobactin fragments THEREFORE it can still cause disease in mice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ABTs helped identify the structure of the outline and was particularly helpful in deciding the order in which data should be introduced in the results section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By identifying the central message and narrative of your scientific text, you can help eliminate tangential information. Additionally, having a handle on the eventual narrative of your research paper can prevent a dense, unorganized data-dump draft.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
